The James G. Barnett Papers
Yale University Music Library
The James G. Barnett Papers
1845-1896
MSS 58
Yale University Music Library
5
(7 boxes)
Music and other papers by and about the British-American composer, conductor, and organist James G. Barnett (d. 1885)
Barnett, James G. (James George), d. 1885
Barnett, John Francis, 1837-1916
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Arrangement
In 5 series as follows: I. Music by James G. Barnett. II. Music by John F. Barnett. III. Music by John Barnett. IV. Music by various composers. V. Addresses, essays, and programs by James G. Barnett.
Scope and Contents
The James G. Barnett Papers consist primarily of manuscript and printed scores and parts for Barnett's orchestral, choral, vocal, and keyboard compositions. The Papers also contain 2 compositions by John Francis Barnett, music by other composers copied by Barnett, and a small number of programs and musical essays.
Biographical / Historical
James G. Barnett was active as a composer, conductor, and organist in Connecticut during the latter half of the nineteenth century. He was born in England, but his date of birth is not known. He arrived in Boston around 1845. The Center Church in Hartford quickly appointed him organist, a position that he held until 1867. Barnett also played a major role in Hartford's concert life. In 1857 he helped found the Beethoven Society, serving as the group's conductor until 1874. Under his leadership, the Society cultivated a diverse repertoire, including Mendelssohn's Elijah, Handel's Samson, Haydn's The Creation, Weber's Oberon, and Rossini's Stabat Mater.
In 1867, Yale College awarded him an honorary doctorate in music. Barnett moved to New Haven around 1875, becoming the organist at St. Thomas Episcopal Church. A heart ailment forced him to withdraw from that position. During his convalescence, he completed The Voice in Praise, a collection of hymns and anthems. Having recuperated, he accepted the organist post at the Second Congregational Church in Fair Haven, which he held until his death in 1885.
Barnett concentrated on vocal music, writing numerous pieces for church services. The Voice in Praise, which contains pieces that can be used in a variety of liturgical contexts, represents the culmination of these efforts. In addition, Barnett composed many large-scale sacred works, notably Life of the Blessed and Christ's Resurrection and Ascension. His secular vocal output includes two operas: The Magician and The Triumph of Spring. Barnett also published The Eclectic Teacher for the Parlor Organ, an instruction manual for the beginning and intermediate student.
Barnett, James G. (James George), d. 1885
- Music by James G. Barnett, Series I
  - Inventory (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anniversary Ode., 8 parts; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General
    Manuscript in ink.
    For chorus and orchestra [lacks choral parts].
    Formerly called Masonic Ode.
  - Begin my soul, the exalted lay., 7 parts; 11 x 27 cm. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    For chorus (SATB) and keyboard [lacks keyboard part].
    From The Voice in Praise.
  - [Benedictus. G major] Benedictus., 16 parts; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    For chorus (SATB).
    English text.
  - [Benedictus. E-flat major] Benedictus., 1 score; 33 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    In Calvary oratorio manuscript, pp. 51-52.
  - Bonum est., 6 parts; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Calvary], 1 score (25 p.); 33 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    manuscript in ink.
    For soloists, chorus, and keyboard.
    Lacks p. 1-4.
    Manuscript also contains various choral pieces and sketches.
  - [Captivity], 1 score (61 p.); 35 cm. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Manuscript incomplete.
  - [Charge of the Light Brigade], 6 parts; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Note on accompanying folder lists performance at the Grand Concert Musical Union on 28 August 1861.
  - Christ's Resurrection and Ascension., 1 score (22 p.) and various vocal parts and sketch pages; 36 cm. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    For soloists, chorus (SATB), and keyboard.
    Programs included for performances on 31 March 1872 and 5 April 1874, South Church, New Britain, CT; 13 April 1884, Second Congregational Church, Fair Haven, CT (selections); programs for undated performances also included.
  - The Christian's Supplication. New York and Chicago: John's Church Co. 1886., 1 score (30 p.); 27 x 18 cm.; 1 handwritten score (11 p.); 25 x 32 cm. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Text by Sir John Bowring.
    2 copies.
  - [Christmas Hymn: O let your mingling voices rise], 7 parts; 21 x 29 cm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Columbia is Free!, Vocal parts and sketches; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    For soloists, chorus (SATB), and children's chorus.
    Text by Mrs. C.T. Preston
    Program for performance on 7 December 1865 at Center Church, Hartford, CT.
  - [Come to me gentle sleep], 1 score; 33 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Vocal Duet and keyboard.
    In Calvary oratorio manuscript, pp. 26-27.
  - Dear is the spot., 1 score (2 p.); 30 x 22 cm. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    4 parts of various sizes.
    For chorus (SATB) and keyboard.
  - Deus Miseratur. Philadelphia: F.A. North, 1886., 1 score (14 p.); 27 x 18 cm. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Eclectic Teacher for the Parlor Organ. Philadelphia: F.A. North, 1883., 168 p.; 23 x 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Instruction manual and music.
    Another copy in Yale Collection, MT202 B261+
  - The Fairy Song. New York: William Hall & Son, no date, 1 score (5 p.); 35 x 27 cm. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    For voice and piano.
    Dedication to Mary L. Kinnan.
  - [Farewell Music for Mr. Goodell], 21 parts; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - [Farewell Music for Rev. Mr. Goodell], 14 parts; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - [Farewell Music for Rev. Mr. Griffin], 11 parts; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    1 sheet of text.
  - [Farewell Music for Mr. Hovey], 5 parts; various sizes. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Farewell Ode to the Old Year, 1 score (8 p.); 35 x 27 cm. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    17 parts and sketches.
    1 printed sheet of text.
    For chorus.
  - Farewell Song (Leafy June is fresh and fair). New York: S.T. Gordon, no date, 1 score (1 p.); 27 x 34 cm. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    For chorus and orchestra [lacks orchestral parts].
    Attributed to J.G. Barnett.
  - Father of mercies hear my prayer. New York: William Hall & Son, no date, 1 score (2 p.); 35 x 27 cm. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Gentle zephyr., 1 score (4 p.); 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Attributed to J.G. Barnett
  - Gloria in Excelsis Deo in G Major, Philadelphia: F.A. North, 1886 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    1 score (9 p.); 28 x 17 cm.
    For chorus (SATB) and organ.
  - Gloria Patris., 7 parts; various sizes. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Gone. Boston: O. Ditson, 1883., 1 score (6 p.); 36 x 27 cm. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Grand installation ode., 20 parts; various sizes. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Programs for performances on 13 September 1871, First Congregational Church, Farmington, CT and 7 May 1884, Second Congregational Church, Fair Haven, CT.
  - Hail Columbia, 1 score (36 p.); 30 x 24 cm. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    For orchestra. Dated February 1845.
  - The heart and the home. New York: William Hall & Son, no date, 1 score (3 p.); 36 x 27 cm. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Text by John Martin.
    Dedicated to Sarah M. Walton.
  - Hebrew Service., 1 score (25 p.); 34 x 26 cm. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Text in transliterated Hebrew.
    Dated May 1878.
  - Holy Father., 1 score; 33 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    In Calvary oratorio manuscript, p. 61.
  - How beautiful show the mountains., 1 score (8 p.); 27 x 35 cm. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    17 parts; various sizes.
    For soprano solo and chorus (SATB).
  - How good and kind., 1 score (24 p.); 33 x 25 cm. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    For chorus (SATB) and orchestra.
  - How lovely are the messengers., 11 parts; various sizes. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - How lovely are thy dwellings., 1 score; 33 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    In Calvary oratorio manuscript, p. 48-50.
  - Hymn (Brightness and beauty)., 1 score (1 p.); 27 x 36 cm. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Copy of manuscript probably lithograph.
    For two high voices
    Text by Mrs. Hawes.
    Dated 1860.
    2 copies
    Program of performance on 28 June 1860 at Center Church, Hartford.
  - Hymn to the Evening., 1 score (20 p.); 33 x 25 cm.; 1 score (34 p.); 33 x 25 cm.; 3 parts; 29 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    2 Programs of performance on 21 June 1874 at South Church, New Britain. 3 programs for performance on 3 December 1882, Second Congregational Church, Fair Haven.
  - In thy presence., 1 score; 33 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    For chorus (SATB)
    In Calvary oratorio manuscript, p. 29.
  - Incline thy ear., 5 parts; 15 x 23 cm. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - [Jubilate. F major] Jubilate., 1 score; 33 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    In Calvary oratorio manuscript, p. 45-46.
  - [Jubilate. B-flat major] Jubilate., 7 parts; 17 x 25 cm. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - [Jubilate. B-flat major] Jubilate., 8 parts; various sizes. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Life of the blessed., 1 score (52 p.); 27 x 33 cm. (Box 7, Folder 98)
    Vocal and instrumental parts various sizes.
    Manuscript in ink. For soloists, chorus, orchestra, and organ.
  - The Magician., 1 voca1 score (140 p.); 35 x 27 cm. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    For three voices and keyboard.
    Text by Henry G. Russell.
    Composed for the Pyne & Harrison Opera Co.
  - Mêléy Quadrilles--1st Set., 1 score (6 p.); 27 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 4l)
    For piano.
  - Music wake thy sweetest strain., 1 score (6 p.); 35 x 27 cm. (Box 3, Folder 42)
    14 parts; 15 x 27 cm.
    Note at top of score reads "also 1862."
  - My faith looks up to thee., 1 score; 33 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    In Calvary oratorio manuscript, p. 42-43.
  - Ode (Bright day of rejoicing)., 1 score (8 p.); 30 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Text by [Philip?] Daniels.
    Performed at the graduation of the Connecticut Normal School on 27 June 1873.
  - Ode (Hand in hand)., 1 score (2 p.); 38 x 26 cm. (Box 3, Folder 44)
    For soloists and chorus.
    Text by the Rev. J.F. Mines.
    Performed at the Centennia1 Anniversary of St. John's Lodge, Hartford on 21 March 1862.
  - Parting Song (We come again to this temple fair), 1 score (7 p.); 26 x 18 cm. (Box 3, Folder 45)
    3 parts; various sizes.
    Text by Sarah E. Knowles.
    3 Programs for a performance at Center Church, Hartford on 28 June 1860.
  - Parting Song (we come again to this temple fair), 1 score (7 p.); 26 x 18 cm. (Box 3, Folder 46)
    Program for a performance at Center Church, Hartford on 28 June 1860. The program also lists a performance at the State Normal School, New Britain on 18 July 1860.
  - Parting Words (Angels from the sainted choirs) New York: S. Pearson, 1859., 1 score (8 p.); 26 x 16 cm. (Box 3, Folder 47)
    Program for performance at Center Church, Hartford on 30 June 1859.
  - Parting Words (Farewell to learning's halls) s.l: n.p., no date, 1 score (1 p.); 26 x 17 cm. (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Text by Mrs. L.H. Sigourney.
  - Parting Words (Praise to him whose power defends us), 1 score (2 p.); 26 x 18 cm.; 1 score (1 p.); 34 x 26 cm. (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Parting Words (Sisters dearly cherished) New York: W.M. Hall & Son, no date, 1 score (4 p.); 27 x 17 cm. (Box 3, Folder 50)
    For chorus (SATB) [lacks accompaniment]
    Written for the closing of the Hartford Female Seminary in June 1858.
  - Parting Words (Within this hallowed temple) New York: S.T. Gordon, no date, 1 score (2 p.); 27 x 18 cm. (Box 3, Folder 51)
    2 handwritten parts (one for keyboard); various sizes
    Written for the closing of the Hartford Female Seminary on 25 June 1857.
  - Polka No. 1., 12 parts; various sizes. (Box 3, Folder 52)
    For orchestra.
  - Praise the Lord., 1 score (3 p.); 27 x 35 cm. (Box 4, Folder 53)
    21 parts; various sizes.
  - [Praise ye the Lord, nos. 1 and 2], 12 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - [Psalms 84 and 122], 1 score (8 p.); 25 x 33 cm. (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Psalm 121., 1 score (2 p.); 39 x 30 cm. (Box 4, Folder 56)
    For quartet and chorus (SATB)
    Dated Thanksgiving 30 November 1854.
  - Regions of life and light., 1 score (11 p.); 35 x 27 cm. (Box 4, Folder 57)
    For soloists, chorus (SATB) and keyboard.
  - The resting place: an ode., 1 score (2 p.); 40 x 30 cm. (Box 4, Folder 58)
    Written for the consecration of Cedar Hill Cemetery.
  - Ruth and Naomi., 27 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - [Selections] From the glad present and its dreamings; The century., 12 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 60)
    Printed program with text.
    Later annotation: East Haven Music.
  - [Selections] (Gently Lord, oh gently lead us]; Lay of freedom., 4 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 61)
    Attributed J.G. Barnett.
  - [Selections] Gloria in Excelsis in F; [Gloria in Excelsis in D-flat] Philadelphia: F.A. North, 1886 [F major]., 1 score (4 p.); 28 x 18 cm. (Box 4, Folder 62)
    11 parts; various sizes.
  - [Selections] J.G. Barnett, Hurrah for the brave volunteers; Meyerbeer (arr.), Grand invocation to the Deity; J.G. Barnett (attr.), Night at sea; Benedict, The ties of friendship; and J.G. Barnett (attr.), Distant bells., 21 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - [Selections] (Lay not up for yourselves]; [Not everyone that saith]., 2 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 64)
    Soprano and alto solos with organ.
  - [Selections] J.G. Barnett, The Lord is my pasture; J.G. Barnett (attr.), Gloria in Excelsis in G; J.G. Barnett (attr.), [Gloria Patris]., 1 score (7 p.); 27 x 35 cm. [The Lord is my pasture]. (Box 4, Folder 65)
    31 parts; various sizes.
    The Lord is my pasture dated November l860.
  - [Selections] J.G. Barnett (attr.), [No richer gem in the diadem]; L.M. Watson, [Blest be the tie that binds]., 7 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - [Selections] The Sabbath day; Hail sacred day of rest., 18 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - [Selections] Tenor parts from Over the dark blue waters; Placid the ocean; Who would stay? (arr. from Weber's Oberon); Lo the early hours of morning; Rest spirit rest; Winds hushed to a sigh (from Night at Sea); Blow gentle gales (soprano part)., 1 part (7 p.); 30 x 24 cm. (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - [Selections] (There be none of Beauty's daughters]; [Erin the tear], 4 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - [Selections] [To thee who weep reignst in realms supernal]; [Weep oh weep, a nation weeps], 19 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Septet., 6 parts; 32 x 25 cm. (Box 5, Folder 71)
    For 2 violins, flute, clarinet, cello, bass, and (piano].
  - [Shade and light], 35 parts; various sizes. (Box 5, Folder 72)
    For soloists, chorus (SATB), and keyboard. [keyboard part missing].
  - [Shout the glad tidings], 18 parts; various sizes. (Box 5, Folder 73)
    For soloists and chorus (SATB)
  - [The strain upraise of joy and praise], 14 parts; various sizes. (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - [Sweet is the scene], 4 parts; 30 x 22 cm. (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Te Deum in F. Philadelphia: F.A. North, 1885., 1 score (16 p.); 27 x 17 cm. (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - [Te Deum in B-flat], 8 parts; various sizes. (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - [To this sacred mountain], 20 parts; various sizes. (Box 5, Folder 78)
    For soloists and chorus (SATB).
  - The Triumph of Spring., 1 vocal score (30 p.); 33 x 25 cm. (Box 5, Folder 79)
    Text by J.G. Barnett.
    Program (including libretto) for performance at Allyn Hall, Hartford, 10 and 11 March 1868.
  - Veni Sancte., 1 score (25 p.); 25 x 33 cm.; 1 score (30 p.); 27 x 33 cm. (Box 5, Folder 80)
    one score dated Center Church, [Hartford], Thanksgiving, 1855.
  - [Venis Sancte, Blest repose when sad and weary], 1 score (6 p.); 30 x 22 cm.; 4 parts; 30 x 22 cm. (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - [Venite Exultemus Domino-Festival] Philadelphia: F.A. North, 1886., 1 score (10 p.); 27 x 16 cm. (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - The voice in praise. Philadelphia: F.A. North, l878., 1 score (164 p.); 28 x 23 cm. (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - [The voice in praise-Selections] Solo vocal parts for Almighty Father; I to the hills will lift mine eyes; When reft of all., 3 parts; various sizes. (Box 5, Folder 83.1)
  - The web of life., 1 score (l7 p.); 24 x 31 cm.; 1 score (8 p.); 35 x 27 cm. (Box 5, Folder 84)
    Text by Gail Hamilton.
  - Zion stands with hills, 1 score; 33 cm. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    In Calvary oratorio manuscript, p. 47.
- Music by John F. Barnett, Series II
  - Sonata London: Augener, no date, 1 score (42 p.); 31 x 23 cm. (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Worthy is the lamb. London and New York: Novello, Ewer & Co., 1896., 1 score (8 p.); 27 x 17 cm. (Box 6, Folder 86)
    For soloists, chorus (SATB), and organ.
- Music by John Barnett, Series III
  - To the omnipotence of the Deity. London: Mayhew, no date, 1 score (90 p.); 37 x 27 cm. (Box 6, Folder 87)
    Text by R. Montgomery.
- Music by various composers, Series IV
  - The ties of friendship, Benedict; 8 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - [Choral Music], 1 score (116 p.); 15 x 24 cm. (Box 6, Folder 88)
    Contents: C.H. Rinck, O Magnify the Lord; Haydn, Mass in B-flat, No. 16 ["Theresienmesse"]; Meyerbeer, See our bark; Haydn, O go your way out of Babylon; Rossini, The God of Israel; Rossini, Lift up the Shawm; Rossini, Rec. And Moses Said; Beethoven, O What Delight.
    Lacks p. 1-5.
  - [Choral Music], 1 score (52 p.); 25 x 14 cm. (Box 6, Folder 89)
    Works for 2-5 voices.
    Contents: [untitled]; Duet: The glad birds are singing; M.P. King, Music from the Wood Daemon; The Alpine Hunters; Hail, thou merry month of May; Horsley, Round: May-Day; Harrington, Duet; Handel (arr.), O lovely place; Sabbantini, In my distress I cried unto the Lord; Handel (arr.)
    Trio.
    Lacks p. 1-9.
  - Overture to Don Pasquale., Donizetti, Gaetano, 1797-1848; 1 score (19 p.); 24 x 29 cm. (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - The nations tremble., Handel, George Frideric, 1685-1759; 1 score (12 p.); 24 x 29 cm. (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - The Holy Dead. New York: Firth, Pond, & Co., no date, Hodges, Faustina Hasse; 1 score (4 p.); 22 x 34 cm. (Box 6, Folder 92)
    Handwritten vocal parts; various sizes.
    For three voices and piano.
    Text by Klopstock, trans. by Longfellow.
  - Macbeth Music., Locke, Matthew; 1 score (7 p.); 24 x 29 cm. (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Grand Invocation Scene., Meyerbeer, Giacomo, 1791-1864; 12 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Ernani Chorus, Verdi, Giuseppe, 1813-1901; 8 parts; 31 x 24 cm. (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Blest be the tie that binds., Watson, L.M.; 7 parts; various sizes. (Box 4, Folder 66)
- Addresses, essays, and programs by James G. Barnett, Series V
  - Church music and its advancement., 1 notebook (18 p.); 21 x 17 cm. (Box 6, Folder 95)
    Lecture read before the Musical Congress in Boston, no date
  - Historical paper of the Beethoven Society read at the celebration of the 15th anniversary of its organization., 1 notebook (44 p.); 22 x 17 cm. (Box 6, Folder 96)
    Dated 24 November 1873.
  - [Program for the Beethoven Society's performance of Haydn's Creation], 3 p.; 30 x 22 cm. (Box 6, Folder 97)
    Performance on 23 October 1873 at Robert's Opera House, Hartford.